I'm sure that, throughout the hundred-thousand-odd years
انا متأكد أنه خلال مئات السنين الماضية
of our species' existence,
لوجودنا
and even before,
و حتى قبل ذلك
our ancestors looked up at the night sky,
قام أجدادنا بالنظر إلى السماء في الليل
and wondered what stars are.
و تساءلوا ما هي النجوم.
Wondering, therefore,
تساءلوا، لأن
how to explain what they saw
كيف يشرحوا ما رأوه
in terms of things unseen.
بأشياء لم يرونها.
Okay, so, most people
إن معظم الناس
only wondered that occasionally, like today,
يتساءلون بالمناسبات فقط، مثل اليوم
in breaks from whatever
ليأخذو قسطاً من الراحة من أي شيئ
normally preoccupied them.
عادة ما يشغلهم
But what normally preoccupied them
ولكن ماهو الشيء الذي عادة ما يشغلهم
also involved yearning to know.
والذي يتضمن أيضاً السعي للمعرفة.
They wished they knew
أنهم تمنوا أن يعرفوا
how to prevent their food supply
كيف يحافظوا على مواردهم الغذائية
from sometimes failing,
من التلف
and how they could rest when they were tired
و كيف يمكنهم الإسترخاء عندما يكونوا متعبين
without risking starvation,
من غير المخاطرة بأن تصيبهم مجاعة
be warmer, cooler, safer,
و كيف يشعرون بالدفئ والبرودة والآمان
in less pain.
بأقل قدر من الالم .
I bet those prehistoric cave artists
إني أراهن أن فنانوا كهوف قبل التاريخ
would have loved to know
أحبوا أن يعرفوا
how to draw better.
كيف يمكنهم الرسم بشكل أفضل
In every aspect of their lives,
في كل ناحية من نواحي حياتهم
they wished for progress, just as we do.
يتمنون التطور مثلنا تماماً.
But they failed, almost completely, to make any.
ولكنهم يفشلون من أن يقوموا بشيء بشكل كامل تقريباً .
They didn't know how to.
لم يكونون يعرفوا كيف .
Discoveries like fire
الإكتشافات مثل النار
happened so rarely, that from an individual's point of view,
تحدث بشكل نادر وذلك من وجهة نظر الفرد
the world never improved.
و أن العالم لن يتطور أبداً .
Nothing new was learned.
وأنه لايوجد شيء جديد تعلمناه
The first clue to the origin of starlight
أول فكرة عن أصل ضوء النجوم
happened as recently as 1899: radioactivity.
حدثت مؤخراً في 1899 ( الإشعاعية ) .
Within 40 years,
خلال أربعين سنة
physicists discovered the whole explanation,
أكتشف علماء الفيزياء التفسير كله
expressed, as usual, in elegant symbols.
في شكل رموز راقية كالعادة .
But never mind the symbols.
لكن لا تهتموا بالرموز .
Think how many discoveries
فكر كم من الإكتشافات
they represent.
قدموا .
Nuclei and nuclear reactions, of course.
تفاعلات الذرة و النواة بالطبع.
But isotopes, particles of electricity,
لكن النظائر، الجسيمات الكهربية
antimatter,
المواد المضادة
neutrinos,
النيوترونات
the conversion of mass to energy -- that's E=mc^2 --
تحويل الكتلة إلى طاقة ( E=mc^2 )
gamma rays,
أشعة غاما،
transmutation.
تحويل عنصر إلى آخر.
That ancient dream that had always eluded the alchemists
ذاك الحلم القديم الذي راود الكيميائيين
was achieved through these same theories
تم تحقيقه عن طريق هذه النظريات نفسها
that explained starlight
وذلك يفسر ضوء النجوم
and other ancient mysteries,
و ألغاز قديمة أخرى
and new, unexpected phenomena.
و ضواهر جديدة وغير متوقعة
That all that, discovered in 40 years,
وكل ذلك تم أكتشافه في اربعين عام
had not been in the previous hundred thousand,
لم تكتشف في آلاف السنوات الماضية
was not for lack of thinking
لم يكن ذلك بسبب قلة التفكير
about stars, and all those other urgent problems they had.
حول النجوم و جميع هذه المشاكل المستعجلة .
They even arrived at answers,
حتى أنهم وجدوا الإجابات
such as myths,
مثل الأساطير
that dominated their lives,
التي سيطرت على حياتهم
yet bore almost no resemblance
ولكن لا تقود بعد
to the truth.
إلى الحقيقة
The tragedy of that protracted stagnation
مآساة الجمود التي طال أمدها
isn't sufficiently recognized, I think.
لم يتم التعرف عليها بشكل فاعل كما اعتقد
These were people with brains of
هؤلاء ناس لديهم عقول
essentially the same design
لها نفس التصميم جوهرياً
that eventually did discover all those things.
اكتشفت كل هذه الأمور في النهاية .
But that ability to make progress
ولكن القدرة على التطور
remained almost unused,
بقيت غير مستخدمة
until the event that
حتى الحدث
revolutionized the human condition
الذي كان بمثابة ثورة في الحالة البشرية
and changed the universe.
و غيرت الكون .
Or so we should hope.
أو هذا ما يجب أن نأمل فيه .
Because that event was the
لأن هذا الحدث
Scientific Revolution,
كان بمثابة ثورة علمية
ever since which our knowledge
حتى قبل معرفتنا
of the physical world,
للعالم الحسي
and of how to adapt it to our wishes,
و كيف نكيفه لآمانينا
has been growing relentlessly.
ظل ينمو بلا هوادة.
Now, what had changed?
الآن ، ماذا تغير ؟
What were people now doing for the first time
ماذا الذي فعله الناس لأول مرة الآن
that made that difference
والذي خلق الفرق
between stagnation
بين الركود
and rapid, open-ended discovery?
والإكتشاف السريع، غير المنتهي؟
How to make that difference
كيف تحقق هذا الفرق ؟
is surely the most important universal truth
تعتبر أكثر الحقائق الكونية أهمية
that it is possible to know.
والممكن معرفتها .
Worryingly, there is no consensus about what it is.
مثيرة للقلق، وليس هناك توافق حولها.
So, I'll tell you.
لذلك، سأخبركم.
But I'll have to backtrack a little first.
ولكن يجب أن أعود للوراء قليلاً .
Before the Scientific Revolution,
إلى ما قبل الثورة العلمية
they believed that everything important, knowable,
حيث أعتقدوا بأن كل شيء مهم و يمكن معرفته
was already known,
كان معروفاً مسبقاً
enshrined in ancient writings, institutions,
المنصوص عليها في الكتابات القديمة، والمؤسسات،
and in some genuinely useful rules of thumb --
وفي بعض القواعد المفيدة حقا من الإبهام --
which were, however, entrenched as dogmas,
والذي مع ذلك، رسخت كعقائد،
along with many falsehoods.
مع العديد مع الأكاذيب.
So they believed that knowledge came from authorities
لذلك فانهم يتعقدون بأن المعرفة تأتي من السلطات
that actually knew very little.
والتي في الحقيقة تعرف القليل فقط .
And therefore progress
و لذلك فإن العملية
depended on learning how to reject
تعتمد على تعلم كيفية رفض
the authority of learned men,
سلطة الرجال المتعلمين
priests, traditions and rulers.
و القساوسة و التقاليد والقوانين
Which is why the Scientific Revolution
و التي تبرر لماذا الثورة العلمية
had to have a wider context.
تحتوي على سياق اوسع :
The Enlightenment, a revolution in how
التنوير، الثورة في كيف أن
people sought knowledge,
الناس تسعى للمعرفة
trying not to rely on authority.
حاول أن لا تعتمد على السلطة
"Take no one's word for it."
" لا تقتنع برأي أحد تماماً "
But that can't be what made the difference.
ولكن لا يمكن أن يكون هذا ما احدث الفرق.
Authorities had been rejected before, many times.
لقد تم رفض السلطات مرات كثيرة من قبل.
And that rarely, if ever,
ونادراً إذا لم يكن أبداً
caused anything like the Scientific Revolution.
سبب أي شيء مثل الثورة العلمية.
At the time, what they thought
وفي هذا الوقت، ما يعتقدون بإنه
distinguished science
علم مميز
was a radical idea about things unseen,
كان عبارة عن فكرة راديكالية حول أشياء لم ترى،
known as empiricism.
عُرِفت بالتجريبية.
All knowledge derives from the senses.
تشتق كل المعرفة من الحواس
Well, we've seen that that can't be true.
حسناً . لقد عرفنا بأن ذلك لا يمكن أن يكون صحيح .
It did help by promoting
إنه يساعد عن طريق التعزيز
observation and experiment.
والملاحظة والتجربة
But, from the outset, it was obvious
ولكن ( من وجهة نظر عامة ) من الواضح
that there was something horribly wrong with it.
أنه هناك أمر خاطئ به .
Knowledge comes from the senses.
المعرفة تأتي من الحواس .
In what language? Certainly not the language of mathematics,
في أي لغة؟ بالطبع أنها ليست لغة الرياضيات
in which, Galileo rightly said,
حيث قال جاليليو
the book of nature is written.
أن كتاب الطبيعة مكتوب.
Look at the world. You don't see equations
أنظر إلى العالم. فإنك لا ترى أسئلة
carved on to the mountainsides.
متعرجة على جوانب الجبال
If you did, it would be because people
إذا رأيت ، فإن ذلك بسبب أن البشر
had carved them.
قاموا بتعريجها.
By the way, why don't we do that?
بالمناسبة ، لماذا لا نقوم بذلك؟
What's wrong with us?
ما بالنا؟
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
Empiricism is inadequate
التجريبية ليست كافية
because, well,
لأن ، حسناً
scientific theories explain the seen in terms of the unseen.
النظريات العلمية تفسر المرئي من منظور غير المرئي
And the unseen, you have to admit,
و غير المعروف يجب عليك أن تعترف بأنه
doesn't come to us through the senses.
لا ياتي لنا عبر الحواس
We don't see those nuclear reactions in stars.
إننا لا نرى هذه التفاعلات النووية في النجوم .
We don't see the origin of species.
و لا نرى أصل الانواع .
We don't see the curvature of space-time,
ولا نرى إنحناء الزمكان.
and other universes.
و العوالم الأخرى .
But we know about those things.
ولكننا نعلم بهذه الأشياء .
How?
كيف ؟
Well, the classic empiricist answer is induction.
حسناً، الإجابة التقليدية المُذهلة هي الإستقراء.
The unseen resembles the seen.
غير المرئي يفسر المرئي .
But it doesn't.
ولكن ذلك غير صحيح .
You know what the clinching evidence was
تعرفون أن ما يحسمه الدليل كان
that space-time is curved?
أن الزمكان مُنحني
It was a photograph, not of space-time,
إنها صورة، لم تكن الزمكان.
but of an eclipse, with a dot there rather than there.
لكن الكسوف، هناك نقطة بدلاً عن هناك.
And the evidence for evolution?
و دليل الثورة ؟
Some rocks and some finches.
بعض الصخور و العصافير.
And parallel universes? Again: dots there,
والعوالم الموازية ؟ أيضاً نقاط
rather than there, on a screen.
بدلاً عن هنالك، على الشاشة
What we see, in all these cases,
ما نراه في هذه الحالات كلها
bears no resemblance to the reality
لا تعكس الواقع
that we conclude is responsible --
نحن نسنتج إلى ان المسؤول
only a long chain of theoretical reasoning
هو مجرد سلسلة طويلة من النظريات المفسرة
and interpretation connects them.
والمترجمة مروبطة مع بعضها .
"Ah!" say creationists.
"آه!" قال الخلق.
"So you admit it's all interpretation.
إذا فإنك تعترف بانها كلها ترجمات .
No one has ever seen evolution.
لا أحد رأى الثور .
We see rocks.
رأينا صخور .
You have your interpretation. We have ours.
لدينا ترجماتنا . نمتلكها .
Yours comes from guesswork,
و ترجماتك تاتي من التخمينات .
ours from the Bible."
و تأتينا من الكتاب المقدس .
But what creationist and empiricists both ignore
بما تجاهله المبتكرون والتجريبيون.
is that, in that sense,
غير أنه، في ذاك المعنى
no one has ever seen a bible either,
لا أحد رأى أبداً الكتاب المُقدس حتى.
that the eye only detects light, which we don't perceive.
ذلك أن العين ترى النور، الذي لا يُمكننا إدراكه.
Brains only detect nerve impulses.
العقول وحدها تكشف النبضات العصبية.
And they don't perceive even those as what they really are,
ولكنها لا تدركها كما هي حقيقة،
namely electrical crackles.
أعني الخشخشة الكهربائية.
So we perceive nothing as what it really is.
أذن نحن لا ندرك شئ من ما هو حقيقة.
Our connection to reality
إتصالنا حقيقي
is never just perception.
ليس فقط مجرد توقع
It's always, as Karl Popper put it,
إنها دوماً، كما وضع كارل الإحتمال،
theory-laden.
موسيقى نظرية.
Scientific knowledge isn't derived from anything.
معرفة العلماء ليست مستمدة من أي شئ.
It's like all knowledge. It's conjectural, guesswork,
إنها ككل معرفة. حدسية، تخمينية،
tested by observation,
مختبرة بالتأمل،
not derived from it.
ليست مستمدة منها.
So, were testable conjectures
إذاً، نحن مُخمنون إختباريون
the great innovation that opened the intellectual prison gates?
الإبتكار العظيم الذي فتح بوابات السجن الفكرية؟
No. Contrary to what's usually said,
لا. عكس ما يقال غالباً،
testability is common,
قابلية الإختبار مشتركة
in myths and all sorts of other irrational modes of thinking.
في الأساطير وجميع أنواع الوسائط الأخرى الغير عقلانية في التفكير.
Any crank claiming the sun will go out next Tuesday
أي مهووس يدعي أن الشمس ستخرج خارجاً في يوم الثلاثاء
has got a testable prediction.
وقد حصل على تنبؤ قابل للإختبار
Consider the ancient Greek myth
بالنظر في الأسطورة اليونانية القديمة
explaining seasons.
التي تشرح الفصول
Hades, God of the Underworld,
الإنحرافات، إله العالم السفلي
kidnaps Persephone, the Goddess of Spring,
يختطف بيرسفوني، إله الربيع،
and negotiates a forced marriage contract,
والتفاوض على عقد الزواج القسري،
requiring her to return regularly, and lets her go.
طُلب منها أن تعود بإنتظام، ويدعونها تذهب.
And each year,
وكل سنة.
she is magically compelled to return.
هي مضطرة للرجوع بصورة سحرية.
And her mother, Demeter,
وأمها، ديميتر،
Goddess of the Earth,
إله الأرض،
is sad, and makes it cold and barren.
حزين، يجعلها باردة وقاحلة.
That myth is testable.
هذه أسطورة قابلة للإختبار.
If winter is caused by Demeter's sadness,
والخريف يحدث بسبب حُزن ديميتر.
then it must happen everywhere on Earth simultaneously.
إذاً يجب أن يحدث في كل مكان في الأرض، بالتساوي.
So if the ancient Greeks had only known that Australia
إذاً لو كان قدماء الأغريق يعرفون فقط أستراليا
is at its warmest when Demeter is at her saddest,
أنها في قمة دفئها بينما ديميتر في قمة حزنها.
they'd have known that their theory is false.
لكانوا قد علموا أن نظريتهم خاطئة.
So what was wrong with that myth,
إذاً ما هو الخطاً في تلك الأسطورة،
and with all pre-scientific thinking,
وكُل ما قبل التفكير العلمي،
and what, then, made that momentous difference?
وماذا، بعد، جعل الأساسيات مختلفة؟
I think there is one thing you have to care about.
أعتقد أنه هنالك شئ واحد لتقلقوا بشأنه.
And that implies
وذلك يتضمن
testability, the scientific method,
قابلية الأختبار، الطريقة العلمية،
the Enlightenment, and everything.
الثقافة، وكل شئ.
And here is the crucial thing.
وإليكم الشيء المصيري
There is such a thing as a defect in a story.
هنالك شئ كالخلل في القصة.
I don't just mean a logical defect. I mean a bad explanation.
لا أعني خلل منطقي فقط. أعني تفسير سيئ.
What does that mean? Well, explanation
ماذا يعني ذلك؟ حسناً، تفسير
is an assertion about what's there, unseen,
هو تأكيد على وجود شيء غير مرئي
that accounts for what's seen.
محسوب على المرئي.
Because the explanatory role
وذلك بحسب الدور التوضيحي.
of Persephone's marriage contract
وعقد زواج بيرسفوني
could be played equally well
قد يكون لعب دوراً متساوياً
by infinitely many other
في أشياء أخرى لا متناهية
ad hoc entities.
مخصصة للكيانات.
Why a marriage contract and not any other reason
لماذا عقد زواج وليس أي سبب آخر
for regular annual action?
لعمل سنوي اعتيادي.؟
Here is one. Persephone wasn't released.
هنا مثال . برسفون ( إبنه زيوس ) لم تكن محررة .
She escaped, and returns every spring
هربت ، وكانت تعود كل ربيع
to take revenge on Hades,
لتنتقم من هاديس ( أخ زيوس ) ،
with her Spring powers.
بقوسها الزنبركى .
She cools his domain with Spring air,
إنها تلطف جو مملكة نفوذه بهواء ربيعي
venting heat up to the surface, creating summer.
وتقوم بتهوية السطع مشكلةً الصيف
That accounts for the same phenomena as the original myth.
وهذا محسوب على الظواهر كأسطورة أصلية
It's equally testable.
وهي قابلة للاختبار بشكل متساوٍ
Yet what it asserts about reality
ولكن ما تؤكده حول الواقع
is, in many ways, the opposite.
هو العكس، وبعدة طرق
And that is possible because
وهذا الشيء ممكن لأن
the details of the original myth
تفاصيل الأسطورة الأصلية
are unrelated to seasons,
غير مرتبطة بالفصول
except via the myth itself.
باستثناء الأسطورة ذاتها
This easy variability
هذه التقلبية البسيطة
is the sign of a bad explanation,
هي دليل لتفسير سيئ
because, without a functional reason to prefer
لأنه، بدون سبب عملي لتفضيل
one of countless variants,
أحد المتغيرات الكثيرة جداً
advocating one of them, in preference to the others,
تدعو إحداها بشكل تفضيلي عن الباقي
is irrational.
هو شيئ غير منطقي
So, for the essence of what
لذا، فإن جوهر
makes the difference to enable progress,
مايشكل الفرق في تحقيق التقدم
seek good explanations,
هو البحث عن التفاسير
the ones that can't be easily varied,
التفاسير التي لا تتغير بسهولة
while still explaining the phenomena.
أثناء تفسير الظواهر
Now, our current explanation of seasons
حالياً، تفسيرنا لظاهرة الطقوس
is that the Earth's axis is tilted like that,
هو أن محور الأرض مائل هكذا
so each hemisphere tilts toward the sun for half the year,
بحيث أن كل نصف كرة يكون مائل باتجاه الشمس لمدة نصف سنة
and away for the other half.
وبعيداً عنها لنصف السنة الثاني
Better put that up.
من الأفضل لنا تعلم ذلك
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
That's a good explanation: hard to vary,
هذا تفسير جيد: من الصعب أن يتغير
because every detail plays a functional role.
لأن كل تفصيل فيه يلعب دوراً فعالاً
For instance, we know, independently of seasons,
على سبيل المثال، نحن نعلم، بشكل مستقل عن الفصول
that surfaces tilted away
أن السطوع التي تميل بعيداً
from radiant heat are heated less,
عن الأشعة تكون أقل حرارة
and that a spinning sphere, in space,
وأن تدوير كرة في الفضاء
points in a constant direction.
يجعلها تدور بشكل متواصل وثابت
And the tilt also explains
والميل أيضاً يفسر
the sun's angle of elevation at different times of year,
ارتفاع زاوية الشمس في مختلف أوقات السنة
and predicts that the seasons
وينبئ أن الفصول
will be out of phase in the two hemispheres.
ستكون لا مرحلية في نصفي الكرة الأرضية
If they'd been observed in phase,
ولو أنها شوهدت أنها مرحلية
the theory would have been refuted.
لدحضت النظرية
But now, the fact that it's also a good explanation,
لكن الآن، الحقيقة أنه تفسير جيد أيضاً
hard to vary, makes the crucial difference.
ومن الصعب أن يتغير، ويشكل اختلاف حاسم
If the ancient Greeks had found out
أنه لو أن اليونانيون القدماء علموا
about seasons in Australia,
عن الفصول في استراليا
they could have easily varied their myth
لكان بإمكانهم تغيير أسطورتهم بسهولة
to predict that.
ليتنبئوا بذلك
For instance, when Demeter is upset,
وعلى سبيل المثال، عندما يكون ديميتير منزعجاً
she banishes heat from her vicinity,
فهي تبعد الحرارة من جوارها
into the other hemisphere, where it makes summer.
إلى نصف الكرة الآخر، حيث يتشكل الصيف
So, being proved wrong by observation,
إذاً، وبالرغم من إثبات خطأهم بالملاحظة
and changing their theory accordingly,
وتغيير نظريتهم على هذا الأساس
still wouldn't have got the ancient Greeks
لم يجعل ذلك اليونانيون القدماء
one jot closer to understanding seasons,
يفهمون الفصول ولو بمقدار ذرة
because their explanation was bad: easy to vary.
لأن تفسيرهم كان سيئاً ومن السهل تغييره
And it's only when an explanation is good
ومايهم هو فقط عندما تكون التفاسير جيدة
that it even matters whether it's testable.
لدرجة تتيح أهمية كونها قابلة للاختبار
If the axis-tilt theory had been refuted,
لو كانت نظرية ميل المحور قد نقضت
its defenders would have had nowhere to go.
لما وجد المدافعون عنها مكان يذهبو إليه
No easily implemented change
لايوجد تغيير قابل للتنفيذ بسهولة
could make that tilt
قد يكون سبب ذلك الميل
cause the same seasons in both hemispheres.
لأنها نفس الفصول في نصفي الكرة الأرضية
The search for hard-to-vary explanations
عملية البحث عن تفاسير غير قابلة للتغيير
is the origin of all progress.
هو أصل أي تقدم
It's the basic regulating principle
إنه المبدأ التنظيمي الأساسي
of the Enlightenment.
للتنوير الفلسفي.
So, in science, two false approaches blight progress.
إذاً، في العلم، خطآن ينهجان تقدم مخرب
One is well known: untestable theories.
الأول معروف جيداً: وهو النظريات الغير قابلة للاختبار
But the more important one is explanationless theories.
لكن الأهم هو النظريات الغير قابلة للتفسير
Whenever you're told that some existing statistical trend will continue,
عندما يتم إخبارك بوجود اتجاه إحصائي سوف يستمر
but you aren't given a hard-to-vary account
ولا يتم إعطائك دليل ثابت
of what causes that trend,
عن الشيء الذي يسبب ذلك الاتجاه
you're being told a wizard did it.
فهذا يعني أن ساحراً قد فعل ذلك
When you are told that carrots have human rights
عندما يتم إخبارك أن الببغاء يتمتع بحقوق الإنسان
because they share half our genes --
لأنها نصف جيناتها تشابه جينات البشر
but not how gene percentages confer rights -- wizard.
وليس كيف تمنح نسبة الجينات الحقوق -- ساحر.
When someone announces that the nature-nurture debate
عندما يعلن أحدهم أن المناقشة المنشأة الطبيعية
has been settled because there is evidence
قد تم تسويتها بسبب وجود دليل
that a given percentage of our
بأنه نسبة معطاة
political opinions are genetically inherited,
من آرائنا السياسة موروثة جينياً
but they don't explain how genes cause opinions,
بدون تفسير كيف أن الجينات تسبب الآراء
they've settled nothing. They are saying that our
فإنهم لم ينجزوا شيئاً, إنهم يقولون
opinions are caused by wizards,
أن آرائنا سببها السحرة.
and presumably so are their own.
ومن المحتمل أن آرائهم سببتها السحرة أيضاً
That the truth consists of
الحقيقة تتألف من
hard to vary assertions about reality
دلائل غير قابلة للتغيير حول الواقع
is the most important fact
هي الحقيقة الأكثر أهمية
about the physical world.
حول العالم الملموس
It's a fact that is, itself, unseen,
إنها حقيقة أنه نفسه غير مرئي.
yet impossible to vary. Thank you.
ومع ذلك من المستحيل أن يتغير
(Applause)
( تصفيق )